<?xml-model
href="https://digitallatin.github.io/guidelines/critical-editions.rng" type="application/xml" 
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model
href="https://digitallatin.github.io/guidelines/critical-editions.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Bellum Alexandrinum, Translation</title>
                <author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/116523553">Cynthia Damon, et al.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding:</resp>
                    <name ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8192-9385">Samuel J. Huskey</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Digital Latin Library</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>650 Parrington Oval</street>
                    <addrLine>Carnegie Building 101</addrLine>
                    <settlement>Norman</settlement>
                    <name>OK</name>
                    <postCode>73071</postCode>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </address>
                <authority>The University of Oklahoma</authority>
                <pubPlace>Norman, OK</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode"
                        >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International Licence (CC BY-SA
                        4.0)</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <p>This is a rendering by many hands, so it is stylistically uneven. The objective was
                to convey the meaning of the Latin syntax. </p>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:id="edition-text">
                <div type="textpart" n="1" xml:id="part1">
                    <p n="1"><seg n="1">With the kindling of the Alexandrian War Caesar summoned his
                            whole fleet from Rhodes and from Syria and Cilicia. He called up archers
                            from Crete, cavalry from Malchus, king of the Nabataeans. He ordered
                            siege engines to be collected from everywhere, grain to be sent, and
                            reinforcements to be brought.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">In the meantime his fortifications were being strengthened every
                            day with defensive works, and every part of the town that seemed to be
                            less secure was being furnished with overhead shelters and covered
                            galleries. Battering rams were carried from buildings into neighboring
                            buildings through holes, and the fortifications were extended into all
                            of the territory that was either cast down in ruins or taken by
                            force.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">For Alexandria is mostly safe from fire, since the buildings lack
                            wooden flooring and are held together by masonry and vaulted structures
                            and covered with rubble and tiles.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Caesar was particularly eager to close off part of the town—the
                            part that a marsh coming in from the south made very narrow—from the
                            rest of the city by employing defensive works and screens.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">His first expectation was that although the city had been divided
                            into two parts his army would be managed according to one plan and
                            authority, and then that it would be possible for support to be provided
                            for his troops when they were struggling and for aid to be brought from
                            the other part of the town, but especially that he would have an
                            abundance of water and fodder. (He had a scanty supply of one of the two
                            (sc. water), and no access at all to the other (sc. fodder).) As to
                            which the marsh could bountifully supply each. </seg></p>

                    <p n="2"><seg n="1">As for the Alexandrians, however, they were subject to no
                            hesitation or delay in conducting their business. For they had sent
                            envoys and recruiting officers into every district—throughout the
                            territory of Egypt and the kingdom—for conducting a levy, and they had
                            brought a large number of weapons and siege engines into the town and
                            had gathered a huge multitude.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Plus, massive workshops of arms were set up in the city. In
                            addition, they had armed the slaves of military age, and the wealthier
                            masters provided these with sustenance and daily pay.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The fortifications of the outlying parts of the town were guarded
                            by an arrangement of this large force. They kept the veteran cohorts
                            available in the most frequented areas of the city so that they could be
                            deployed for bringing aid with fresh strength in whichever area there
                            was fighting.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">They had blocked off all the roads and alleyways with a triple
                            wall—it was built with square stones and was at least forty feet
                            high—and fortified the lower parts of the city with very tall towers,
                            each with ten stories.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">In addition, they had cobbled together moveable towers with the
                            same number of stories. After mounting these on rollers, with ropes and
                            pack animals †placed opposite†, they would move them on level streets
                            into whichever part (sc. of the city) they wanted. </seg></p>
                    <p n="3"><seg n="1">The city, extremely abundant and well supplied, furnished
                            all manner of provisions. The men themselves, clever and extremely keen,
                            replicated with such ingenuity things they had seen made by us that our
                            men seemed to have imitated their works, and they were discovering many
                            things of their own accord and simultaneously attacking our
                            fortifications and defending their own.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Plus, their leaders kept pushing these points in councils and
                            assemblies: that the Roman people gradually were coming into the habit
                            of occupying the kingdom; that a few years prior Aulus Gabinius had been
                            in Egypt with an army; that Pompey had withdrawn there in his flight;
                            that Caesar had come with his troops, but that nothing had been
                            accomplished by Pompey's death to deter Caesar from staying there;</seg>
                        <seg n="4">that if they did not drive him out, a province would come into
                            being out of the kingdom, and that this must be done quickly. For
                            Caesar, they said, shut off by storms because of the time of year, could
                            not receive support from across the sea. </seg></p>
                    <p n="4"><seg n="1">Meanwhile a dispute had arisen between Achillas, who was in
                            charge of the veteran army, and Arsinoe, the younger daughter of king
                            Ptolemy, as was indicated above. Although each was plotting against the
                            other and wanting to possess overall control, Arsinoe struck first
                            through the eunuch Ganymede, her tutor, and killed Achillas.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">With him dead she began to take complete control without any
                            partner or guardian. The army was handed over to Ganymedes. When he took
                            up the office he increased the bounty for soldiers and managed the
                            remaining tasks with equal diligence.</seg></p>
                    <p n="5"><seg n="1">Almost all of Alexandria has channels bored out beneath it,
                            and it has conduits extending to the Nile (i.e., the Nile canal) through
                            which water is led into private houses. And this (sc. water) gradually
                            in an interval of time becomes clear and settles.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">It is this that owners of buildings and their households are
                            accustomed to use. For that which is carried by the Nile River is so
                            muddy and thick that it causes many different diseases. But the common
                            people and the masses are necessarily content with it, since there are
                            no fountains in the entire city. Nevertheless, the watercourse was in
                            the part of the city controlled by the Alexandrians.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Ganymedes was reminded by this fact that our men could be cut off
                            from their water supply. These, distributed throughout the neighborhoods
                            for the purpose of protecting the fortifications, were using water from
                            private buildings drawn from conduits and wells. </seg></p>
                    <p n="6"><seg n="1">When this plan was approved he set about a great and
                            difficult task. After having blocked all the conduits and closed off all
                            the areas of the city that were occupied by him he strove to draw a huge
                            amount of water from the sea with wheeled mechanisms. This (sc. water)
                            he constantly poured from higher locations (i.e., from locations in the
                            now blocked pipes that were below the blockage but above the private
                            buildings' cisterns) into Caesar's territory.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For this reason the water drawn from the closest buildings (i.e.,
                            those closest to the place(s) where sea water was injected into the
                            system) was a little saltier than usual, and why this occurred was a
                            source of great puzzlement for people. They did not really trust
                            themselves, since people lower down said that they were using water of
                            the same kind and flavor as they were accustomed to before, and they
                            began making comparisons amongst themselves in public. And by tasting
                            the waters they recognized how much the waters differed.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">But shortly thereafter the water that was closer (sc. to the
                            place(s) where sea water was coming in) was wholly undrinkable and the
                            lower water (i.e., the water in recipients that were further away) was
                            now found to be more spoiled and saltier.</seg></p>
                    <p n="7"><seg n="1">And when, with this development, uncertainty was removed, so
                            great a fear invaded that all felt themselves to have been brought to
                            the brink of danger and some said that Caesar was delaying giving (i.e.,
                            was in no hurry to give) the order to embark, and others were much more
                            seriously alarmed about their plight because, as they thought, it was
                            not going to be possible to keep the Alexandrians ignorant while making
                            preparations for a withdrawal, since they were separated from themselves
                            by so little distance, nor was taking refuge on the ships going to be an
                            option with the Alexandrians nearby and in pursuit.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Moreover, there was a large crowd of townspeople in Caesar's
                            district, whom he had not removed from their homes because they were
                            making an open show of being loyal to our men and seemed to have cut
                            their ties with their own side, so that I would have to defend the
                            Alexandrians, saying that they are neither deceitful nor impetuous, and
                            much verbiage would be spent to no purpose.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">But when their community and character are considered
                            simultaneously, no one can doubt that this race is perfectly prepared
                            for treachery. </seg></p>
                    <p n="8"><seg n="1">Caesar alleviated the fear of his men with reasoning and
                            encouragement. He declared that if wells were dug fresh water could be
                            found, as all shores naturally possess veins of fresh water.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Even if the nature of the Egyptian shore was different from all
                            the rest, he said, since they had freedom of movement on the sea and the
                            enemy did not have a fleet, they could not be prevented from going after
                            water with their ships daily, from either the left, from Paratonium, or
                            the right, from the island, routes that, being different, were not going
                            to be shut down by adverse winds at one and the same time.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Retreat was certainly not in the plans, not only for those who
                            considered their dignity of prime importance but not even for those who
                            thought of nothing other than their own lives.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Only with great difficulty were the enemy's frontal attacks being
                            sustained from the fortifications. Once the fortifications were
                            abandoned, they could not equal the enemy in position or number.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Moreover, boarding the ships involved a long delay and great
                            difficulty, especially from skiffs. The Alexandrians, by contrast, were
                            possessed of the greatest mobility and knowledge of the positions and
                            the buildings.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">These people, particularly insolent in the face of victory, would
                            run ahead and gain possession of both the higher ground and the
                            buildings. Thus they would prevent our men from fleeing in the ships.
                            Accordingly, they should forget the idea and consider that they must
                            win, whatever the cost. </seg></p>
                    <p n="9"><seg n="1">When he had made this speech to his men and everyone's
                            spirits were roused he gave his centurions the assignment that pausing
                            their work elsewhere they should concentrate on digging wells and not
                            pause for any portion of the night.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Once this assignment was taken in hand and the spirits of all
                            were spurred on to exertion, in a single night a great quantity of fresh
                            water was discovered. In this way the Alexandrians' laborious schemes
                            and huge efforts were counteracted by a brief exertion.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Two days later the thirty-seventh legion, made up of Pompeian
                            troops who had surrendered, having been put onto ships by Domitius
                            Calvinus with grain, arms, projectiles, and catapults, was conveyed to
                            the shore of Africa somewhat beyond Alexandria.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">These ships were prevented from reaching the harbor by the East
                            wind, which blew continuously for many days. However, locations
                            throughout that region are excellent for holding anchors. Since they
                            were detained in that place for a long time and oppressed by a shortage
                            of water they made Caesar aware of their plight by means of a swift
                            ship. </seg></p>
                    <p n="10"><seg n="1">In order to take consideration in person as to what seemed
                            best to be done, Caesar boarded a ship and ordered the whole fleet to
                            follow him—without, however, putting any of our soldiers on board,
                            since, as he was going away for a rather long time, he did not want to
                            leave the fortifications exposed.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">When they had approached the place that is called Chersonensus
                            and had set the oarsmen on shore in order to fetch water, some of these,
                            when they had advanced too far from the ships for the sake of plunder,
                            were captured by the enemy cavalry.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">From these men they (i.e., the enemy) learned that Caesar himself
                            had come with his fleet and that he did not have any soldiers on his
                            ships. Once aware of this they came to believe that Fortune had bestowed
                            upon them an opportunity for accomplishing a great success.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Thus they equipped all the seaworthy ships they possessed with
                            soldiers and fell in with Caesar as he was returning with his
                            fleet.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Caesar did not want to fight on that day for two reasons: first,
                            he had no soldiers on his ships and then, the action itself was taking
                            place after the tenth hour of the day. The night, however, would bring
                            greater assurance to the enemy, it seemed, who trusted in their
                            knowledge of the land. Furthermore, he would be bereft of the benefit of
                            encouraging his troops, since no exhortation that could comment upon
                            neither courage nor slackness would be sufficient to the purpose.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">For these reasons Caesar led back towards the land those ships
                            that he could, to a place where he did not anticipate they would be
                            followed.</seg></p>
                    <p n="11"><seg n="1">There was one Rhodian ship on Caesar's right wing in a
                            position far from the rest. When the enemies saw this ship they did not
                            restrain themselves, and with a concerted attack four decked and several
                            open ships advanced against it.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Caesar was compelled to give aid to the ship so as to avoid
                            incurring a shameful insult in the sight of his own men. And yet he
                            judged that if things ended rather badly for the (ship's) men the
                            outcome would be deserved.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The battle was waged with great exertion on the part of the
                            Rhodians who, although they excelled in both skill and courage in every
                            engagement, did not shrink from bearing the entire burden especially on
                            that occasion to prevent people from thinking that any harm had been
                            suffered by the fault of their men.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Hence the battle turned into a great success. One of the enemy's
                            quadriremes was captured, another was sunk, two were stripped of all
                            their marines. Furthermore, a great multitude of soldiers in the
                            remaining ships were slain.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Had night not split up the battle, Caesar would have become
                            master of the entire enemy fleet.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">While the enemies were thoroughly frightened by this injury,
                            Caesar towed the transport ships to Alexandria against a gentle wind,
                            with his own ships as victors. </seg></p>
                    <p n="12"><seg n="1">The Alexandrians were so crushed by this defeat, since they
                            now saw themselves conquered not by the courage of the fighters but by
                            the skill of the mariners, for whom both <gap reason="lost"/> in/from
                            (?) the higher locations they were being supported, so that (?) they
                            could be defended from the buildings and interposed all the wood as a
                            barrier, because they feared an attack by our fleet even on land.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">The very same people, after Ganymedes assured them in council
                            that he would both restore those (sc. ships) that had been lost and
                            increase their number, began with great hope and confidence to repair
                            the old ships and quite diligently to apply and devote themselves to
                            this matter.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">And although they had lost more than a hundred and ten warships
                            in the port and docks, nevertheless they did not discard the thought of
                            repairing the fleet.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">For they saw that Caesar's reinforcements could not be brought
                            (sc. to him), nor supplies, if they themselves prevailed with their
                            fleet. In addition, as seafaring men belonging to a maritime city and
                            region and trained in daily practice from boyhood, they wanted to take
                            refuge in that natural and familiar advantage and perceived how much
                            they had accomplished with very small vessels. And so they took to
                            preparing the fleet with all zeal. </seg></p>
                    <p n="13"><seg n="1">Guards had been set up at all the mouths of the Nile for
                            the sake of collecting customs fees and there were old ships in the
                            hidden docks of the court, which they had not used for sailing for many
                            years. The latter they restored, the former they recalled to
                            Alexandria.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Oars were lacking. They took the roofs off porticos, gymnasia,
                            and public buildings and made use of the beams as oars. Their natural
                            resourcefulness supplied one thing, the abundance of the city
                            another.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Finally, they were not preparing for a long voyage but serving
                            the need of the present time and saw that the fighting would have to be
                            done in the port itself.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">And so in a few days, contrary to everyone's opinion, they made
                            twenty-two quadriremes and five quinqueremes. To these they added many
                            smaller open boats, and after testing what each of them could do in the
                            harbor by way of rowing they embarked suitable soldiers and outfited
                            them completely for fighting.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Caesar had nine Rhodian ships—for although ten had been sent one
                            had foundered off the Egyptian coast en route—eight Pontic ships, five
                            Lycian ships, and twelve from Asia. Of these ten were quinqueremes and
                            quadriremes, the rest were smaller than this size and many of them
                            open.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">Nevertheless, convinced of the courage of his soldiers and
                            knowing the forces of the enemy he prepared to do battle.</seg></p>
                    <p n="14"><seg n="1">When it reached the point that each had confidence in his
                            side, Caesar sailed around Pharos with his fleet and set his ships
                            opposite the enemy. On the right wing he placed the men of Rhodes, on
                            the left the men of Pontus. Between them he left a space of four hundred
                            paces, which seemed to be enough for deploying up the ships.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Behind this line he arranged the remaining ships as a reserve. He
                            determined which should follow which and which should come to the aid of
                            which, and gave the orders.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Without hesitation the Alexandrians brought out and arranged
                            their fleet for battle. In the front they placed 22 ships; they set up
                            the rest as reserves in a second line.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">They also brought out a great number of smaller ships and skiffs
                            with fire-darts (lit. with darts and fires), in case the multitude
                            itself and the noise and flame could bring anything of terror to our
                            men.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Between the two fleets were shallows with a narrow passage. These
                            extend toward the region of Africa. (For this is what they say, that
                            half of Alexandria is part of Asia.). On both sides there was a rather
                            long wait to see by which of the two the crossing would be initiated,
                            since it seemed that those who entered, if the situation turned out
                            worse for them, would be more impeded from deploying their ships and
                            from retreating.</seg></p>
                    <p n="15"><seg n="1">Euphranor was in charge of the Rhodian ships, a man to be
                            compared in his greatness of heart and his virtue more with our men than
                            with the Greeks.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He, on account of his very conspicuous knowledge and greatness of
                            heart, was selected by the Rhodians to be in charge of the fleet.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When he noticed the Caesar's <supplied reason="lost"
                                >delay</supplied> he said, “You seem to me, Caesar, to be afraid
                            that if you enter the shallows with your boats first, you will be forced
                            to fight before you can deploy the rest of the fleet. Entrust the matter
                            to us.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">We will endure the brunt of the battle — we will not disappoint
                            your trust — until the others can follow us. For them to boast fr any
                            longer in our sight is a source of great disgrace and pain for
                            us.”</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Encouraging him and presenting him with all manner of praise
                            Caesar gave the signal for battle. When four (sc. ships) had moved
                            forward beyond the shallows, the Alexandrians surrounded the Rhodian
                            ships and made an attack on them.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">They (sc. the Rhodians) stood firm and deployed themselves with
                            skill and cunning. And their training was so effective that although the
                            numbers were unequal no ship was exposed sideways to the enemy, no
                            ship's oars were stripped off; in fact they (i.e., the Rhodians or the
                            Rhodian ships) continually confronted those coming against them.</seg>
                        <seg n="7">Meanwhile the others followed. Then they necessarily departed
                            from skill on account of the narrowness of the place and the whole
                            struggle stood on virtue.</seg>
                        <seg n="8">Indeed there was no one in Alexandria, of our men or of the
                            townspeople, <supplied reason="lost">except</supplied> those
                            concentrating on work or combat, who did not seek the highest roofs and
                            from every viewpoint take a place for the spectacle and demand victory
                            for their own side from the immortal gods with prayers and
                            offerings.</seg></p>
                    <p n="16"><seg n="1">The issue of contention, however, was not at all equal in
                            the battle. For our men, once beaten back, had no escape route either by
                            land or sea if defeated, and if they were victorious everything would
                            remain unresolved. The enemy, if they had the advantage with their
                            ships, would have power over everything, but if they proved weaker,
                            would have other ways to try their luck (lit. would test the fortune
                            that remained).</seg>
                        <seg n="2">At the same time it seemed distressing and miserable that a very
                            few men were involved in a decisive fight about the bulk &lt;of the
                            army&gt; and about the safety of everyone. If any one of them fell short
                            in spirit or courage, the rest, who had had no opportunity of fighting
                            for themselves, would have to look out.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">In the previous days Caesar had explained these things to his men
                            repeatedly, so that they would fight with greater spirit because they
                            saw that the safety of all had been entrusted to them.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">By the same argument each man, accompanying a messmate, friend,
                            or companion, implored him not to disappoint his own opinion and that of
                            everyone else, since their judgement was responsible for his being
                            chosen and setting out to fight.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">And so they fought in such a frame of mind that skill and cunning
                            brought no help to the Alexandrians, though they were sailors and
                            seafarers, and the large number did not benefit those with a greater
                            number of ships, and men chosen for their virtue from so great a
                            multitude of men could not equal the virtue of our men.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">One quinquereme was taken in this battle and a bireme, with their
                            fighters and rowers, and three were sunk, while all of ours were
                            unharmed.</seg>
                        <seg n="7">The rest took flight to the nearby town. The (townspeople)
                            protected them from the ramparts and overhanging buildings and prevented
                            our men from going closer. </seg></p>
                    <p n="17"><seg n="1">So that this could not happen to him repeatedly, Caesar
                            thought that he ought to strive to bring the island and the jetty
                            extending to the island into his power, whatever the cost.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For since he had mostly completed his works in the town, he was
                            confident that an attempt could be made on &lt;both the latter&gt; and
                            the former at the same time.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Having adopted this plan, he placed in small vessels and skiffs
                            ten cohorts and the picked men belonging to his light-armed force and
                            whichever of the Gallic horsemen he deemed suitable. On one side of the
                            island &lt;e.g., he landed his footsoldiers, on the other side&gt; he
                            attacked with decked ships in order to divide the (sc. enemy) forces,
                            with great rewards offered to whoever seized the island first. </seg>
                        <seg n="4">At first, equally matched, they withstood the attack of our men,
                            for at the same moment they were both fighting back from the roofs of
                            the buildings and mounting an armed defense of the shore—where on
                            account of the difficulty of the location an easy approach was not given
                            to our men—and nimbly and skillfully patrolling the position's narrows
                            with their skiffs and five warships.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">But as soon as few of our men set foot on the shore, after
                            getting to know the terrain and testing the shallows, and others
                            followed these, and they made a resolute attack upon those who had taken
                            a position on the level shore, all the men of Pharos turned their
                            backs.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">With these men beaten back, <gap reason="lost"/> and with the
                            guard of the port abandoned, they steered the ships toward the shore and
                            the village and rushed forth from the ships to defend the
                            buildings.</seg></p>
                    <p n="18"><seg n="1">But they were unable to hold themselves within this
                            defensive position for very long, even though the type of buildings was
                            not dissimilar to those in Alexandria (to compare smaller things to
                            greater), and lofty connecting tower blocks took the place of a wall,
                            nor had our men come prepared with ladders or brushwood bundles or the
                            remaining materials for making an assault.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">But fear seizes the mind and judgment from men and weakens their
                            limbs. So it happened then.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The same men who were confident that on a fair and level plain
                            they were our equals, terrified by the flight of their men and the death
                            of a few, did not dare make a stand in buildings with a height of 30
                            feet, and they threw themselves into the sea along the jetty and they
                            swam the 800-pace distance to the town.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Many of these men were nonetheless captured and killed, but the
                            number of captives was 6,000 altogether.</seg></p>
                    <p n="19"><seg n="1">Letting the soldiers take the plunder, Caesar commanded
                            that the buildings be ransacked and he fortified a stronghold near the
                            bridge closer to Pharos and placed a garrison there.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">In their flight the men of Pharos had abandoned this bridge; as
                            for the one that was more secure and closer to the city, the
                            Alexandrians were guarding it. But on the next day Caesar attacked it
                            for a similar reason, because he saw that, with these two under his
                            control, naval sorties and sudden raids would be utterly out of the
                            question.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">And using catapults and arrows from his ships he had already
                            expelled those who were holding the place under their protection, driven
                            them back into the town, and landed the equivalent of three cohorts.
                            (For the tight quarters permitted no more to get themselves into
                            position. The rest of his troops remained at their posts on the
                            ships.)</seg>
                        <seg n="4">After accomplishing this he commanded that the bridge be
                            fortified against the enemy and that where the ships had a way out—an
                            arch had been built and the bridge was supported by it—the area be
                            filled with rocks and blocked.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">With the one of these tasks completed, such that no skiff at all
                            was able to get out, and with the other task begun, all of the
                            Alexandrians' forces flung themselves out of the city and took a
                            position in the wider area up against our bridge fortifications. At the
                            same time they positioned the vessels that they had been in the habit of
                            sending out through the bridges to burn our transports near the
                            jetty.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">We were fighting from the bridge and jetty; they were fighting
                            from the flat area facing the bridge and the ships alongside the
                            jetty.</seg></p>
                    <p n="20"><seg n="1">With Caesar occupied in these matters and exhorting the
                            troops, a great number of oarsmen and marines launched themselves from
                            our warships onto the jetty.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">A portion of them were carried by an eagerness to watch, a
                            portion even by a desire to fight. At first these repelled the enemy
                            vessels from the jetty with stones and slings, and they seemed to be
                            accomplishing much with the quantity of projectiles.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">But after a few Alexandrians dared to disembark from their ships
                            beyond that point, on their open flank, our men, just as they had
                            advanced without standards and fixed ranks, without order, in like
                            manner they began to retreat rashly into the ships.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">More Alexandrians, spurred on by their flight, were disembarking
                            from the ships and pursuing our men, whose dismay had intensified (OR,
                            with Landgraf's emendation: starting a more aggressive pursuit of our
                            men, who had been thrown into confusion). At the same time, those who
                            had remained in the warships were hurrying to pull in the ladders and
                            push the ships away from the shore to prevent the enemy from capturing
                            the ships.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Thrown into confusion by all of these events, our troops of the
                            three cohorts that had been stationed on the bridge and the first part
                            of the jetty, when they heard the clamor behind them, saw the flight of
                            their own men, and faced a huge number of incoming projectiles, fearing
                            lest they be surrounded in the rear and entirely cut off from retreat by
                            the departure of the ships, abandoned the defenses begun on the bridge
                            and with a great rush headed in agitation towards the ships.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">A portion of them, after reaching the nearest ships, were sunk by
                            the multitude of men and their weight, a portion, pausing and hesitating
                            over what plan should be taken, were killed by the Alexandrians. Some
                            with a more fortunate outcome reached the unencumbered ships at anchor
                            and escaped unharmed; a few, raising their shields and relying on an
                            enterprising spirit, swam to nearby vessels. </seg></p>
                    <p n="21"><seg n="1">As long as Caesar was able by exhortation to keep his men
                            at the bridge and defenses, he stayed on, sharing their danger (lit. was
                            involved in the same danger). After he noticed that everyone was
                            retreating, he withdrew himself into his own vessel.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">And when a great number of men following him there swarmed in,
                            and no opportunity either of maneuvering or pushing back from the shore
                            was given, suspecting that what did happen would happen he launched
                            himself from the vessel and swam to the ships that were stationed
                            further out.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">From there, sending skiffs to assist his struggling men, he saved
                            some. As for his vessel, weighed down by the great number of men it
                            perished together with the men.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">In this battle around 400 were lost from the number of the
                            legionary troops and a slightly greater number of oarsmen and
                            marines.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">The Alexandrians fortified a stronghold in that spot with
                            substantial defenses and many siege engines, and after removing the
                            rocks from the water they used the place freely afterwards for sending
                            out vessels. </seg></p>
                    <p n="22"><seg n="1">Our men were so far from being thrown into confusion by
                            this defeat that, roused and provoked, they made extra efforts in
                            attacking the enemy's fortifications.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">In the daily battles, whenever a chance had come their way, with
                            the Alexandrians running forward and making sorties, <gap reason="lost"
                            /> combat <gap reason="lost"/> to be checked †greatly† by fortifications
                            and the burning eagerness of the soldiers. Nor was Caesar's widespread
                            exhortation able to attain the level of the legions' effort or desire
                            for fighting, so that they had to be deterred and restrained from
                            exceptionally dangerous forms of combat rather than worked up for
                            fighting. </seg></p>
                    <p n="23"><seg n="1">The Alexandrians, since they saw that the Romans were both
                            steadied by successes and spurred on by reverses, and since they did not
                            know any third outcome of war by which they could become steadier
                            themselves, as we are able to comprehend by conjecture, either having
                            been advised by friends of the king who were inside Caesar's defenses,
                            or with their own previously-made plan having been made acceptable to
                            the king through secret messengers, they sent envoys to Caesar (saying
                            that) he should release the king and allow him to cross over to his own
                            people.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For the whole multitude, they said, fed up with the girl's
                            offensiveness, with a regent as ruler, and with Ganymedes' extremely
                            cruel dominion, was prepared to do what the king ordered; and if they
                            came into Caesar's trust and friendship by his authority, there would be
                            no fear of any danger preventing the multitude from surrendering.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="24"><seg n="1">Caesar, although he knew well that the people were
                            deceitful and always thinking something other than what they were
                            pretending, nevertheless decided that there was utility in giving an
                            indulgence to the petitioners. For he believed that the king would
                            remain loyal after he was released if their feelings somehow accorded
                            with what they were asking for, but that if they wanted to have the king
                            as a leader for waging war (which was a better fit with their nature),
                            it would be more splendid and honorable undertaking for him to wage war
                            against a king rather than against a band of refugees and
                            fugitives.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Therefore, after urging the king to consider the interests of his
                            ancestral kingdom, to spare <surplus>even</surplus> his most outstanding
                            country, which had been disfigured by shameful conflagrations and
                            demolitions, to recall his citizens to sanity and then preserve them,
                            and to display his loyalty to the Roman people and to himself, since he
                            (Caesar) believed in him so much that he sent him to armed enemies,
                            grasping his right hand in his own right hand he began to dismiss the
                            boy already an adult in age.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">But the royal spirit, educated in the most deceitful
                            disciplines—and so that he would not fall short of the customs of his
                            race—in tears began to beg Caesar instead not to send him away, saying
                            that to him his very kingdom was not more pleasing than the sight of
                            Caesar.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">After the boy's tears were suppressed an emotional Caesar,
                            himself affirming that he (Ptolemy) would quickly be with him (Caesar)
                            if he felt that way, dismissed him to his own people.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">As if released from from the starting gate onto an open track,
                            Ptolemy began to wage so vigorous a war against Caesar that he seemed to
                            have shed from joy the tears that he had produced in their
                            meeting.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">Many legates, friends, officers, and soldiers of Caesar were glad
                            that this had happened, because, as they thought, his excessive
                            benevolence had been cheated by the deceits of a boy. As if in truth
                            Caesar had done it led by generosity alone and not with a most prudent
                            plan. </seg></p>
                    <p n="25"><seg n="1">When the Alexandrians, after acquiring a leader, observed
                            that they became no stronger nor did the Romans become more sluggish,
                            and when, with the soldiers mocking the king's age and weakness, they
                            took great offence and saw that they were not accomplishing anything,
                            and when rumors arose that Caesar's substantial garrisons were being
                            brought along the land route from Syria and Cilicia (a thing that had
                            not yet been heard by Caesar), they decided to intercept the provisions
                            that were being shipped for our men by sea.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">And so, with unencumbered vessels placed on duty in suitable
                            places near Canopus, they began to lie in wait for our ships
                            †supplies?†.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When this was announced to Caesar, he commanded his whole fleet
                            to be unencumbered and deployed. He placed Tiberius Nero in command of
                            it (sc. the fleet). The Rhodian ships set out in this fleet, among them
                            Euphranor, without whom no naval battle had ever—or even with inadequate
                            success—been accomplished.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">But Fortune, who for the most part keeps those whom she has
                            adorned with many favors for a harsher fall, pursued Euphranor unlike
                            the Fortune of earlier occasions.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">For after they reached Canopus and the fleet deployed on each
                            side had come to grips, and Euphranor, by his own custom, had been the
                            first to engage and pierced through and sunk an enemy quadrireme, he,
                            pursuing the next ship too far—since the rest were not following quickly
                            enough—was surrounded by the Alexandrians.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">No one carried aid to him, either because they thought that there
                            was enough protection for him because of his valor and luck or because
                            they were afraid for their lives. So out of all in that battle the one
                            man who conducted the affair well was the only one who perished, along
                            with his victorious quadrireme.</seg></p>
                    <p n="26"><seg n="1">Around the same time, Mithridates of Pergamum, a man of
                            great prestige in Pergamum and of great wit and valor in war, and
                            loyalty and dignity in his friendship with Caesar, having been sent into
                            Syria and Cilicia at the start of the Alexandrian War for the sake of
                            summoning reinforcements, with a great number of troops (which he had
                            put together quickly thanks to both the most eager desire of the
                            citizens and his own diligence),</seg>
                        <seg n="2">brought (sc. the troops) to Pelusium by a land route, where Egypt
                            is joined with Syria. And as for this town, held by Achillas’ strong
                            garrison because of the location’s convenience (for all Egypt is deemed
                            to be fortified, as if by locks, with respect to naval attack by Pharos,
                            with respect to land attack by Pelusium), Mithridates, having surrounded
                            it suddenly with a great number of troops, although the multifarious
                            garrison was fighting back stubbornly, brought it under his authority on
                            the very day of the attack and installed his own garrison there, thanks
                            to both the number of his own troops—he kept substituting intact troops
                            for the wounded and the weary—and his perseverance and steadiness for
                            fighting.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Therefore, with this matter carried off well, he headed toward
                            Alexandria, toward Caesar. And he had pacified all the areas through
                            which he was making his way by the authority that is usually at hand for
                            the victor, and had brought them into friendship with Caesar.</seg></p>
                    <p n="27"><seg n="1">There is a place not far from Alexandria, the most famous
                            place of those regions, which is called the Delta. It took this name
                            from its resemblance to the letter. For a certain portion of the Nile
                            river, after a diversion, connects with the sea in two branches,
                            gradually leaving a space in the middle between them, the branches being
                            very far apart at the shore.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Since the king learned that Mithridates was approaching this
                            place and knew he must cross the river, he sent a large force against
                            him, by which he believed Mithridates could be conquered or wiped out,
                            or certainly detained.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Although he desired that Mithridates be conquered, the king
                            considered it sufficient that Mithridates be detained by him, cut off
                            from Caesar.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">The first troops able to cross the river from the Delta and meet
                            Mithridates started a battle, eager to deprive those who were following
                            behind of a share of the victory.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Mithridates withstood their attack with great prudence and
                            steadfastness [of his virtues and the imprudence of the Alexandrians],
                            his camp having been fortified according to our custom. But when he saw
                            them approaching the fortifications recklessly and immoderately, he made
                            sallies from every side and killed a great number of their men.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">If the rest had not hidden themselves, using their familiarity
                            with the territory, and in part withdrawn into the ships they had used
                            to cross the river, they would have been completely wiped out.</seg>
                        <seg n="7">When these men had revived themselves a little from that scare,
                            they joined themselves to those who were following and began to attack
                            Mithridates again.</seg></p>
                    <p n="28"><seg n="1">A messenger was sent from Mithridates to Caesar in order to
                            relate his success. The king learned about these same events from his
                            own men.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Thus at nearly the same time the king set out to crush
                            Mithridates and Caesar to relieve him. The king used the quicker route
                            by boat via the Nile river, in which he had a large fleet in readiness.
                            Caesar was unwilling to use the same route, so as to avoid fighting a
                            naval battle in the river, but taking a roundabout route by the sea that
                            is said to belong to a part of Africa, as I explained above, he
                            nonetheless fell in with the king's forces before the king could attack
                            Mithridates, and welcomed a victorious Mithridates with his army
                            intact.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The king had encamped with his troops in a place with natural
                            fortification, as it was in itself higher than the plain that lay
                            beneath it on all sides. On three sides, moreover, it was protected by
                            fortifications of different sorts: one side had been situated adjacent
                            to the Nile river, another laid out in an extremely lofty position so
                            that the position would constitute part of the stronghold, and the third
                            was hemmed in by a swamp.</seg></p>
                    <p n="29"><seg n="1">Between the stronghold and Caesar’s route passed a narrow
                            river with extremely high banks, which flowed into the Nile. It was
                            about seven miles distant from the king’s stronghold.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">When the king learned that Caesar was coming by that route, he
                            sent his entire cavalry and select light infantry to that river; they
                            were to prevent Caesar from crossing and engage from the banks in a
                            lop-sided long-range battle: for courage made no headway and cowardice
                            met with no danger.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">This situation inflamed our soldiers and cavalry with resentment
                            that the contest with the Alexandrians was lasting so long in an
                            indecisive battle.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Thus, at the same moment a portion of the German cavalry, after
                            scattering in search of fords, swam across the river where the banks
                            were rather low, and the legions, after cutting down huge trees that
                            were long enough to touch both banks, toppling them forward and piling
                            on a makeshift roadbed, crossed the river.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">The enemy was so utterly terrified of their attack that they set
                            their hopes of safety on flight. Yet this was in vain, for a few from
                            that flight made it back to the king, while all the remaining multitude
                            was slain. </seg></p>
                    <p n="30"><seg n="1">After this most notable success Caesar, since he thought
                            that his sudden approach would strike great terror into the
                            Alexandrians, immediately pushed forward as a victor to the king's
                            camp.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">But when he observed that this (camp) was surrounded by a
                            substantial fortification and protected by the nature of its position,
                            and saw the dense mass of armed men stationed on the rampart, he was
                            unwilling to have his soldiers, weary with marching and fighting, move
                            up to attack the camp. Therefore, he pitched camp, leaving no great
                            distance (between it and) the enemy.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">On the following day, Caesar attacked and took the fort that the
                            king had built in the nearest village not far distant from his own
                            stronghold and joined to the its fortification by means of outworks so
                            as to hold onto the village. Caesar used all of his forces, not because
                            he thought it would be difficult to accomplish this by using a smaller
                            number of soldiers, but so that, with the Alexandrians thoroughly
                            unnerved by that victory, he could attack the king's stronghold
                            directly.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">And so the soldiers pursued the Alexandrians retreating from the
                            fort into the stronghold at a run, and without stopping moved up to the
                            fortifications and began to fight an extremely fierce long-range
                            battle.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Our men had an approach for attack from two areas: one, which I
                            explained had an unencumbered approach, the other, which had a
                            moderate-sized space between the stronghold and the river Nile.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">The largest and most carefully picked contingent of the
                            Alexandrians was defending the area that afforded the easiest approach,
                            but the men who were fighting near the river Nile were having the most
                            success in repelling and wounding our men. For our men were being
                            pierced by projectiles from different directions, from the front by
                            projectiles coming from the stronghold's rampart, from the rear by
                            projectiles coming from the river, on which many ships manned with
                            slingers and archers were attacking our men.</seg></p>
                    <p n="31"><seg n="1">When Caesar saw that his soldiers could fight no more
                            vigorously, and yet that little headway was being made owing to the
                            difficulty of their positions, and when he noticed that the Alexandrians
                            had neglected their stronghold's most elevated position both because it
                            provided its own defense and because, in their eagerness in some cases
                            to fight, in others to look on, the men had rushed down to the position
                            in which there was fighting, he ordered three cohorts to encircle the
                            stronghold and to attack the most elevated position, and he put
                            Carfulenus in command of them, a man outstanding in both greatness of
                            spirit and knowledge of military affairs.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Upon their arrival, with a small number defending the
                            fortifications while our men fought with extreme vigor, the
                            Alexandrians, terrified by the noise and the fighting in a new location,
                            began to scatter in a panic into every part of the stronghold.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The spirits of our men were so incited by the enemy's confusion
                            that they captured positions at nearly the same time from all
                            directions, the stronghold's highest point, however, first. Running down
                            from that point our men killed a great multitude of the enemy in the
                            stronghold.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Many Alexandrians fleeing this danger hurled themselves en masse
                            from the rampart into the area that was joined to the river.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">The first of these were crushed in a great heap right in the
                            fortification's trench, and then the rest had an easier escape.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">It is agreed that the king himself fled from the camp and then,
                            after being received aboard ship, perished when the vessel was sunk by
                            the large number of men who were swimming to the nearest ships.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="32"><seg n="1">This affair was conducted with the utmost success and
                            rapidity, and thereafter Caesar, with the confidence arising from a
                            great victory hastened with his cavalry to Alexandria by the nearest
                            overland route and entered as victor through the quarter of the town
                            that was in the hands of the enemy garrison.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">His plan proved completely correct: after hearing about the
                            battle the enemy was no longer going to contemplate war.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Upon arrival he gained a fitting return for valour and
                            magnanimity, for the entire population of townsfolk threw down their
                            weapons and abandoned their fortifications. Then, after donning the
                            attire in which suppliants customarily placate rulers with prayers and
                            bringing out all the sacred emblems by whose sanctity they were
                            accustomed to entreat the offended and angry hearts of their kings, they
                            hastened to Caesar as he arrived and surrendered themselves to
                            him.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Caesar took them under his protection and consoled them, then
                            went through the enemy fortifications into his own part of the town
                            greatly cheered by his own men, who were happy about the good fortune
                            not only of the war itself and the fighting but also of the way he
                            arrived (in Alexandria). [According to Orosius, 6.16.1, there were
                            12,000 prisoners of war and 70 captured ships.] </seg></p>
                    <p n="33"><seg n="1">Having made himself master of Egypt and Alexandria, Caesar
                            appointed as rulers those whom Ptolemaeus had written down in his will
                            and entreated the Roman people that they not be changed.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For since the elder of the two boys, the king, was gone, Caesar
                            handed over the kingdom to the younger one and to the elder of the two
                            daughters, Cleopatra, who had remained under his protection and within
                            his defenses; the younger daughter, Arsinoe—I showed earlier that
                            Ganymedes long ruled immoderately in her name—he decided to remove from
                            the realm, lest some new dissension arise again at the instigation of
                            turbulent men, before the dominion of the rulers was consolidated by the
                            passage of time.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">As for the legions, taking the veteran Sixth taken away with him
                            he left the rest there, so that the dominion of these rulers would be
                            more stable, rulers who could enjoy neither the affection of their
                            people, because they had remained faithfully in the friendship of
                            Caesar, nor the authority of a long-established reign, having been in
                            place as rulers for a small number days.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">At the same time he deemed it relevant to the dignity of our
                            empire and to public expediency that, if the rulers remained loyal, they
                            be protected by our garrisons; if they were ungrateful, they could be
                            held in check by those same garrisons. Thus with all these things
                            completed and put in place, he (Caesar) himself set out by way of land
                            into Syria.</seg></p>
                    <p n="34"><seg n="1">While these events took place in Egypt, King Deiotarus came
                            to Domitius Calvinus, to whom Caesar had given Asia and the nearby
                            provinces to be governed, to beg him not to allow Lesser Armenia, his
                            own kingdom, or Cappadocia, the kingdom of Ariobarzanes, to be possessed
                            and destroyed by Pharnaces, (saying that) unless they (i.e., the kings)
                            were freed from this evil, they were unable to do what had been ordered
                            and to pay the money promised to Caesar.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Domitius, since he not only deemed that money was necessary for
                            settling military expenses but also determined that it was a shameful
                            thing for the Roman people and for victorious C. Caesar and a
                            disreputable thing for himself that the kingdoms of allies and friends
                            be occupied by a foreign king, immediately sent messengers to Pharnaces,
                            (ordering him) to withdraw from Armenia and Cappadocia and not to test
                            the strength of the right and majesty of the Roman people in the
                            circumstance of civil war.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Since he thought that this warning was going to have greater
                            force if he approached those regions more closely with his army, having
                            set out to the legions he led one of three, the Thirty-Sixth, with him,
                            sent to Caesar in Egypt the two summoned in Caesar's letters. (One of
                            these did not arrive in the Alexandrian war, because it had been sent by
                            a terrestrial route through Syria.)</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Cn. Domitius added to the Thirty-Sixth legion two from Deiotarus
                            that he had built up with our discipline and armament for many years,
                            plus 100 horsemen, and took the same number from Ariobarzanes.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">He sent P. Sestius to the quaestor C. Plaetorius, (ordering him)
                            to lead the legion that had been formed out of hastily raised soldiers
                            in Pontus, and Quintus Patisius to Cilicia for the purpose of summoning
                            reinforcements. All these forces quickly assembled in Comana (i.e.,
                            Comana Pontica) by the order of Domitius.</seg></p>
                    <p n="35"><seg n="1">Meanwhile the ambassadors brought back replies from
                            Pharnaces: that he had withdrawn from Cappadocia but retaken Lesser
                            Armenia, which he ought to possess by right, on his father's account.
                            Finally, the matter of that kingdom should be preserved untouched for
                            Caesar. For he (Pharnaces) was ready to do what he (Caesar) had
                            decided.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Since [P.] Domitius noted that Pharnaces had withdrawn from
                            Cappadocia motivated not by free choice but by necessity, because he was
                            able (he believed) to defend Armenia, adjacent to his own kingdom, more
                            easily than the more remote Cappadocia, and because he had thought that
                            Domitius was going to bring along all three legions, and had remained
                            quite audaciously in Armenia once he (Pharnaces) realized that two of
                            these had been sent to Caesar, he (Domitius) began to insist that he
                            (Pharnaces) withdraw from that kingdom, too. For his right to
                            Cappadocia, Domitius said, was no different than his right to Armenia,
                            nor was there justification for his demand that the matter be left
                            untouched for the arrival of Caesar, for something was "untouched" if it
                            was the same as it had been.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">With these replies having been given, Domitius set out into
                            Armenia with the forces that I recorded above, and he began to make a
                            journey via higher ground. (For leaving Pontus by way of Comana
                            &lt;there is&gt; an elevated, wooded ridge stretching into Lesser
                            Armenia, and this ridge forms the boundary separating Cappadocia from
                            Armenia.) And &lt;it is agreed&gt; that these are the indubitable
                            advantages of this route: the fact that on higher ground no sudden
                            attack of enemies could occur, and the fact that Cappadocia, adjacent to
                            these ridges, was going to supply a great abundance of
                            provision(s).</seg></p>
                    <p n="36"><seg n="1">Meanwhile Pharnaces sent several embassies to Domitius to
                            negotiate about peace and bear the king's gifts to Domitius.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He (sc. Domitius) kept rejecting all these things firmly and
                            responding to the ambassadors that nothing was going to be more
                            important to him than recovering the dignity of the Roman people and the
                            kingdoms of the allies.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">With long and uninterrupted marches having been completed, when
                            he arrived at Nicopolis—this town located in Lesser Armenia was itself
                            in a level place, but with high mountains as barriers on two sides at a
                            significant remove from the town—he pitched his camp around 7 miles away
                            from Nicopolis.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Since a narrow and obstructed place had to be traversed (sc. by
                            anyone approaching Nicopolis) from this camp, Pharnaces set selected
                            infantry and almost all his cavalry in an ambush. Moreover, he ordered a
                            large quantity of livestock to be scattered within the pass and the
                            peasants and townsfolk to linger in these places,</seg>
                        <seg n="5">so that, whether Domitius traversed this narrow spot as friend or
                            enemy, he would have no suspicion of an ambush when he noticed that both
                            livestock and men were moving about in the fields as if at the arrival
                            of friends, or, if he came as if into enemy territory, his soldiers
                            would be scattered in plundering booty and slaughtered piecemeal.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="37"><seg n="1">Although he was conducting these operations, Pharnaces
                            nevertheless continued to send legates to Domitius concerning peace and
                            friendship, because he believed that by this very strategy Domitius
                            could be more easily deceived.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Conversely, the hope of peace gave Domitius cause for delaying in
                            the same camp (i.e., for staying where he was, about 7 miles from
                            Nicopolis). Thus Pharnaces, once the opportunity of the most recent
                            moment had been lost, because he feared that his ambush might be made
                            known, recalled his men into the camp.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">On the following day Domitius approached nearer to Nicopolis and
                            set up camp near town. While our troops strengthened this camp,
                            Pharnaces arrayed his battle line according to his custom and
                            habit.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">For with the battle line drawn as a single straight line in the
                            front, the wings were strengthened by three reserves each. Following the
                            same rationale these (i.e., three-fold reserves) were positioned in the
                            middle of his battle line, with single lines arrayed in the two
                            intervals to the right and left (sc. of the middle of the line).</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Domitius finished the work that had been started on the camp,
                            with part of his troops having been stationed in front of the
                            rampart.</seg></p>
                    <p n="38"><seg n="1">The next night Pharnaces, with messengers having been
                            intercepted who were carrying letters to Domitius concerning the affairs
                            of Alexandria, learned that Caesar was situated in great danger and that
                            it was being demanded of Domitius that he send reinforcements to Caesar
                            as soon as possible and that he himself advance closer to Alexandria
                            through Syria.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">With this having been learned, Pharnaces reckoned it to be
                            tantamount to victory if he was able to drag out the time, because he
                            thought that it was necessary for Domitius to decamp quickly.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Thus where he thought there was the easiest approach from the
                            town and most advantageous location for our men for waging battle, he
                            extended two straight trenches, four feet in depth, with a not
                            particularly large space having been left between them, to the place
                            beyond which he had determined not to extend his line.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">He always drew up his battle line between these trenches; he
                            stationed his entire cavalry, however, beyond the trench on the sides.
                            They were going to be able to be useful in no other way and surpassed
                            our cavalry by a great number. </seg></p>
                    <p n="39"><seg n="1">Domitius, however, because he was disturbed more by
                            Caesar's danger than his own and judged that he would not safely break
                            camp if he sought again the terms that he had rejected or departed
                            without cause, led the army out of the nearby camp and into battle
                            formation.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He stationed the thirty-sixth legion on the right wing, the
                            Pontic legion on the left. He moved the legions of Deiotarus together
                            into the middle of the line—but he nevertheless left them a very narrow
                            section of the front—with the remaining cohorts positioned as reserves.
                            With the battle line on both sides having been drawn up thus there was
                            an advance for the purpose of fighting.</seg></p>
                    <p n="40"><seg n="1">With the signal having been given on both sides at the same
                            time there was a charge. The fighting was fierce and various. For the
                            thirty-sixth legion, after it made an attack beyond the trench against
                            the cavalry of the king, waged so successful a battle as to come under
                            the walls of the town, cross the trench, and attack the enemy from
                            behind.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">But on the other side the Pontic legion, when it had withdrawn a
                            small distance facing the enemies but had tried to circumvent and get
                            across the trench so that it could attack the enemy on its open flank,
                            was stopped and overwhelmed in very act of crossing the trench. The
                            legions of Deiotarus, however, barely withstood the attack.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Thus the royal forces, victorious on his right wing and in the
                            middle of the line, turned themselves toward the thirty-sixth legion.
                            This nevertheless withstood the attack of the victors bravely.
                            Surrounded by a great mass of foes, fighting with great resolution, (the
                            legion) drew itself into a circle near the base of the mountains, where
                            Pharnaces did not wish to follow owing to the location's unfavorable
                            nature.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Thus with the Pontic legion having been almost completely lost,
                            and with a great part of Deiotarus’ soldiers having been killed, the
                            thirty-sixth legion took themselves to a higher location with no more
                            than two hundred and fifty having been lost.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Some distinguished and illustrious men died in this battle,
                            Romans of equestrian status. After incurring such a setback Domitius
                            nevertheless gathered the remains of (his) scattered army and withdrew
                            them into Asia through Cappadocia by safe roads. </seg></p>
                    <p n="41"><seg n="1">Pharnaces, carried away by his successes, since he was
                            hoping that what he wanted concerning Caesar (would occur), occupied
                            Pontus with all his forces. And there, acting as both a conqueror and an
                            exceptionally cruel king, since he was set on (having) his paternal
                            holdings with a more prosperous outcome, he laid waste to many towns,
                            plundered the goods of both Roman and Pontic citizens,</seg>
                        <seg n="2">established tortures in regards to those who had something
                            commendable of beauty and age, those (tortures) that were more pitiable
                            than death. And since no one defended Pontum, he began to hold it,
                            boasting that he had retaken his paternal kingdom.</seg></p>
                    <p n="42"><seg n="1">Around that same time a setback occurred in Illyricum. This
                            province had been held in the preceding months not only without disgrace
                            but even with praise.</seg>
                        <seg n="2"> Moreover, Quintus Cornificius, a quaestor of Caesar’s with
                            propraetorian powers, having been sent to this province in the summer
                            with two legions, even though the province was minimally stocked for
                            sustaining armies and had been exhausted and laid waste by the nearby
                            war and rebellions, nevertheless with his foresight and
                            attentiveness—since he took great care that he not advance rashly
                            anywhere—both reclaimed and defended <surplus>it</surplus>.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">For instance, he stormed numerous strongholds positioned in
                            elevated locales, the advantageousness of which kept encouraging the
                            stronghold commanders to execute raids and undertake military campaigns,
                            and presented his soldiers with the booty (which, even if meagre, was
                            nevertheless appreciated, so great was the desperation of the province,
                            especially since the booty had been acquired through valor). And when
                            Octavius, after the flight that followed the battle of Pharsalus,
                            arrived in that area with a great fleet, Cornificius had gained
                            possession of Octavius' scattered ships using a few ships of the
                            Iadertini, a people whose singular service to the state had remained
                            firm. The result was that, with these ships added to those of his
                            allies, he was able to contend in battle with something akin to a
                            fleet.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">When, Caesar, the victor, was pursuing Cn. Pompeius in the most
                            extreme opposite part of the earth and heard that numerous adversaries,
                            after collecting those left after the flight, had arrived in Illyricum,
                            owing to its proximity to Macedonia, he sent a message to Gabinius,
                            [bidding him] that he set out with his legions of recruits, which had
                            been conscripted just recently, for Illyricum. After joining his forces
                            with Q. Cornificus, he was to dispel any danger inflicted on the
                            province; if, however, the province could not be secured with forces
                            that were not large, he was to lead his legions into Macedonia.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">For Caesar believed that the entire area and region would revive
                            the war, so long as Cn. Pompeius was alive. </seg></p>
                    <p n="43"><seg n="1">When Gabinius came to Illyricum during the wintry and
                            difficult time of the year, whether thinking that the province was more
                            fully stocked, or attributing a great deal to the luck of the victorious
                            Caesar, or confident in his own courage and expertise (having often
                            taken risks with this in his wars, he had executed great successes under
                            his own leadership and auspices), he neither derived support from the
                            resources of the province, which had become desolate in some parts,
                            unreliable in others, nor had the ability to convey provisions, the sea
                            being closed to ships by storms, and under the constraint of great
                            difficulties he waged the war not as he wished, but as was
                            necessary.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Thus, when he was forced to raid towns or strongholds in the most
                            extreme weather on account of his shortage of supplies, he repeatedly
                            suffered misfortunes and was regarded by the locals with such contempt
                            that, while retreating to the coastal town, Salona, whose inhabitants
                            were exceptionally brave and loyal Roman citizens, he was forced to
                            engage in battle on the march.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">After losing more than two thousand infantrymen, thirty-eight
                            centurions, five tribunes in this battle, he retreated with the rest of
                            his forces to Salona and, under pressure from extreme difficulty in
                            everything, within a few months passed away there from illness. And both
                            his ill-luck while alive and his sudden death gave Octavius much hope of
                            acquiring the province. As for him, however, both luck, a most potent
                            factor in wars—along with the diligence of Cornificius—and the bravery
                            of Vatinius did not allow him a very long involvement in success.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="44"><seg n="1">When Vatinius was in Brundisium, after having learned of
                            the things that took place in Illyricum, since he was being summoned by
                            Cornificius' frequent letters to provide aid to the province, and since
                            he was hearing that Marcus Octavius had made pacts with the barbarians
                            and in many places was attacking the garrisons of our soldiers partly in
                            person with a fleet, partly with infantry forces through the agency of
                            barbarians, and although, being affected by poor health, in bodily
                            strength he could barely keep up with his spirit, he nevertheless
                            overcame with his courage the disadvantage of nature and the
                            difficulties of both the winter and the hasty preparation.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For since he had few warships in the harbor, he sent a letter to
                            Achaia to Quintus Calenus asking that he send a fleet to him.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Since this was happening later than the danger in which our men
                            found themselves demanded—they were not able to fend off the attack of
                            Octavius—he mounted beaks on the swift ships, whose number was quite
                            large but whose bulk was by no means appropriate enough for
                            fighting.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">He added these to the warships and, having increased the fleet's
                            numerical strength by putting veteran soldiers on board (he had a great
                            number of these from all the legions, who had been left behind among the
                            sick in Brundisium when his army was being transported to Greece), he
                            set out to Illyricum. <surplus>There</surplus> he took back a few
                            coastal towns that had revolted and surrendered themselves to Octavius,
                            and others, which remained adamant in their decision, he sailed past,
                            and he did not bring upon himself a delay and exigency for any reason
                            that might prevent him from pursuing Octavius himself as quickly as
                            possible.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">With his arrival he forced Octavius, who was attacking Epidaurus,
                            where a garrison of ours was, by land and sea, to disengage the attack,
                            and he took back our garrison.</seg></p>
                    <p n="45"><seg n="1">When Octavius learned that Vatinius had a navy largely
                            composed from small ships built for speed, being confident in his own
                            navy he stopped at the island of Tauris. Vatinius, in pursuit, was
                            sailing in this area, not because he knew that Octavius had stopped
                            there, but rather because he had decided to follow him after Octavius
                            had gone some distance ahead.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">When Vatinius came closer to Tauris (keeping his ships at a
                            distance from one another since the weather was stormy and there was no
                            suspicion of the enemy) he all of a sudden spotted a ship sailing his
                            way, with the yards lowered to mid-mast and equipped with
                            soldiers.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When he noticed this, he quickly ordered that the sails be
                            reefed, the yards be lowered, and that the soldiers arm themselves.
                            Having raised the banner with which he was accustomed to give the
                            battle-sign, he started signaling that the ships that were right behind
                            him do the same thing.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Vatinius’ soldiers began preparing themselves under sudden
                            pressure. Octavius’ soldiers, already prepared, set forth from the
                            harbor one after another. A battle line forms on both sides: that of
                            Octavius with a more orderly arrangement, that of Vatinius better
                            equipped in terms of soldiers’ morale.</seg></p>
                    <p n="46"><seg n="1">Although Vatinius realized that he was inferior both with
                            regards to the ships’ size and their number, he preferred to entrust the
                            matter to a chance engagement. Thus, he attacked first, driving his
                            quinquereme against the quadrireme of Octavius himself.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">As Octavius was rowing against him with utmost speed and bravery,
                            the opposing ships rushed together with their beaks clashing so
                            furiously that the ship of Octavius, her beak shattered, was trapped in
                            the timber.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The battle was going on fiercely elsewhere as well, and there was
                            a rush towards the leaders especially. Since everyone was coming to his
                            own leader’s aid, a large battle developed at close quarters in the
                            narrow strait of the sea.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">The more opportunity for combat was given, once the ships had
                            come together, the greater the superiority of Vatinius' soldiers. With
                            admirable boldness they were not hesitating to jump over from their
                            vessels onto enemy ships, and, once the engagement was brought to equal
                            terms, being by far superior in bravery, they began to fight with
                            success.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">The quadrireme of Octavius himself sank, while many other ships
                            were captured or sunk after being punctured by beaks. The soldiers of
                            Octavius were partly slaughtered on the ships, partly toppled into the
                            sea.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">Octavius himself boarded a skiff. And when many boarded it in
                            flight—the skiff having sunk—Octavius, although wounded, managed to swim
                            to his little pirate vessel.</seg>
                        <seg n="7">Being taken in there, when the night had dispersed the battle, he
                            escaped by sail in a large storm. A few of his ships that chance had
                            spared from the disaster followed him.</seg></p>
                    <p n="47"><seg n="1">But Vatinius, with the affair having been carried off well,
                            sounded a retreat and, as victor, withdrew himself with all of his men
                            uninjured into the port from which Octavius’ fleet had gone forward for
                            the purpose of fighting.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">From that battle he gained possession of one penteris, two
                            triremes, eight two-banked galleys, and several of Octavius’ oarsmen.
                            And after spending the following day there while repairing his own and
                            the captured ships, two days later he hastened to the island of Issa,
                            because he believed that Octavius had withdrawn himself there in
                            flight.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">On the island there was a town, the most famous of those regions
                            and thoroughly tied to Octavius.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">And when Vatinius arrived there the townsfolk gave themselves up
                            as suppliants to Vatinius, and he learned that Octavius himself, the
                            wind being favorable, had made for the region of Greece with a few small
                            ships, so that from there he might head for Sicily and then
                            Africa.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Thus, in a short space, with the affair having been conducted
                            most brilliantly, with the province having been regained and returned to
                            Cornificius, with the fleet of the enemy having been expelled from that
                            entire zone, he, as victor, withdrew himself to Brundisium with his army
                            and fleet uninjured.</seg></p>
                    <p n="48"><seg n="1">However, at the times in which Caesar was besieging Pompey
                            at Dyrrachium and was conducting things successfully at Palaepharsalus
                            and was fighting at Alexandria not only with great danger but also with
                            a greater rumor of danger, Quintus Cassius Longinus, having been left
                            behind in Spain as the propraetor for the sake of holding the further
                            province, owing either to the habit of his nature or to the animosity
                            towards that province that he had adopted as a quaestor after he was
                            wounded there in an ambush, had created significant additions of
                            animosity against himself—and he could have learned of it either from
                            self-awareness, since he believed the province's feelings about him to
                            be reciprocal, or from the many indications and testimonies of those who
                            had difficulty disguising their hatred—and desired to counterbalance the
                            hatred of the province with the affection of the army.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Accordingly, as soon as he assembled the army into one place, he
                            promised one hundred sesterces each to the soldiers, and not long after,
                            when in Lusitania he had captured the town of Medubriga and Mount
                            Herminius, to which the Medubrigensians had fled, and he was addressed
                            as imperator there, he presented the soldiers with one hundred sesterces
                            each.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Moreover, he granted many and great rewards to individuals, which
                            put on display his love of the army at present. However, little by
                            little and secretly he was diminishing military discipline and
                            strictness.</seg></p>
                    <p n="49"><seg n="1">Having established the legions in their various winter
                            quarters, Cassius went to Corduba for the purpose of hearing legal
                            cases, and he decided to pay off debt contracted in the province by
                            means of extremely heavy burdens on the province. And as the custom of
                            largesse demands, the specious pretext of generosity was used, but the
                            intended beneficiary of the majority of the requests was the
                            donor.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Funds were requisitioned from the wealthy, and Longinus not only
                            permitted but even forced these to be set down for him (i.e., in his
                            account books) as expenditures. At this same time frivolous lawsuits,
                            too, were launched against the crowd of wealthy men, and no kind of
                            profit, either great and apparent or small and sordid, was neglected,
                            such that the commander’s residence and tribunal were uninvolved with
                            it.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">No one who could make at least some outlay was not either
                            constrained by a guarantee or listed among the accused. Thus great
                            anxiety about personal peril, too, was added to expenses and damage to
                            family fortunes. </seg></p>
                    <p n="50"><seg n="1">For these reasons it happened that, when Longinus did the
                            same thing as commander that he had done as quaestor, the provincials
                            again initiated similar plans about killing him.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Several members of his inner circle intensified the provincials'
                            hatred. These, although they were involved in that notorious partnership
                            in theft, nevertheless hated the man in whose name they were committing
                            crimes, and were in the habit of crediting to themselves whatever they
                            had seized and assigning to Cassius whatever sums were due for payment
                            or subject to claims.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">He enrolled a new fifth legion. The hatred grew from the
                            conscription itself and from the expense of the additional legion. A
                            contingent of three thousand cavalrymen was filled and equipped at very
                            great expense. And the province was given no repose.</seg></p>
                    <p n="51"><seg n="1">In the meantime, he received a letter from Caesar, saying
                            that he should transfer his army to Africa and should go through
                            Mauretania to the borders of Numidia because it was thought that Iuba
                            had sent substantial reinforcements for Gnaeus Pompeius and was about to
                            send more.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">After he had received the letter he was animated by
                            uncharacteristic readiness because, as he saw it, so great an
                            opportunity—in the form of new provinces and an extremely fertile
                            kingdom—had been offered to him.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Because of this, he himself left for Lusitania in order to summon
                            legions and to gather auxiliary troops. To certain people he gave the
                            task that grain and a hundred ships should be prepared and that monetary
                            contributions should be defined and requisitioned so that nothing would
                            be delayed when he returned.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">For neither effort nor watchfulness were missing in Cassius,
                            especially when he wanted something.</seg></p>
                    <p n="52"><seg n="1">After the army was collected in a single place and the camp
                            had been set up near Cordoba, he explained in front of the assembly of
                            soldiers what things he was obliged to carry out on Caesar’s command,
                            and he promised them, when he had transferred them to Mauretania, to
                            give each 100 sesterces. The fifth legion, he said, would stay in
                            Spain.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">After the assembly he returned to Cordoba and on the very same
                            day in the afternoon, when he was going to the basilica, a certain
                            Minucius Silon, a client of Lucius Racilius, gave him a petition, as if
                            he was demanding something from him in the manner of a soldier. Then,
                            when Silon had insinuated himself behind Racilius (for he covered one
                            side of Cassius) as if he was seeking an answer—room had quickly been
                            made for him—he grabbed Cassius, who was facing away from him, with his
                            left hand and with his right struck him twice with a dagger.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">As a clamor arose there was an attack by all of the conspirators.
                            Munatius Flaccus stabbed the nearest attendant with his sword. After
                            this one was killed, he injured the officer Quintus Cassius.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">At that point Titus Vasius and Marcus Mercello with similar
                            audacity helped their townsman Flaccus. For they were all from Italica.
                            But Lucius Licinius Squillus rushed up to Longinus himself and wounded
                            him lying there with light blows.</seg></p>
                    <p n="53"><seg n="1">People rushed together to defend Cassius. For he was always
                            accustomed to have an armed escort of Berones and numerous
                            veterans.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">By those the rest of the people who were following to participate
                            in the massacre were excluded. In this group were Calpurnius Salvianus
                            and Manilius Tusculus.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Minucius was overpowered while fleeing among the outcrops on the
                            route, and after Cassius had been carried back to his house he was taken
                            to him. Racilius moved to the adjacent house of a friend until he could
                            learn with certainty that Cassius had been finished off.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Laterensis hurried to the camp happy, since he had no doubt about
                            it, and congratulated soldiers of the indigenous and second legions,
                            whom he knew to be particularly hostile to Cassius. He was raised up
                            onto the tribunal by the crowd and declared praetor.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">For nobody either born in the province, like the soldiers of the
                            indigenous legion, or effectively provincial from their long stay (in
                            this number was the second legion), did not agree with the entire
                            province in their hatred for Cassius. As for the 30th and 21st legions,
                            Caesar had assigned them to Longinus after enrollment in Italy a few
                            months earlier. The fifth legion had recently been assembled there (sc.
                            in Spain).</seg></p>
                    <p n="54"><seg n="1">Meanwhile, notice was brought to Laterensis that Cassius
                            was alive. Laterensis, being more moved by sorrow than unsettled at this
                            news, revived himself quickly and set out to visit Cassius.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Upon learning about this matter the 30th legion took its
                            standards to Corduba to bring help to its commander. The 21st did the
                            same. The 5th followed them.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When two legions were left in the camp, the soldiers of the
                            second legion, fearing lest they be left solitary and lest it become
                            evident from that what their feelings (sc. about the matter) were,
                            followed the lead of the previous ones. The indigenous legion remained
                            steadfast in its opinion and was not moved from its position by any
                            fear.</seg></p>
                    <p n="55"><seg n="1">Cassius ordered those who were named as accomplices to the
                            murder to be seized. Keeping 30 cohorts, he sent the fifth legion back
                            to camp.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">From Minucius' evidence he learned that Lucius Racilius, Lucius
                            Laterensis, and Annius Scapula, a provincial of the highest standing and
                            influence and as closely connected to himself as Laterensis and
                            Racilius, had taken part in the same conspiracy (sc. as Minucius), and
                            he did not detain his sorrow for long before he ordered them to be
                            killed.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">He handed over Minucius to his freedmen to be tortured, likewise
                            Calpurnius Salvianus, who gave evidence and increased the number of
                            conspirators—truthfully, as some think, but as others protest, under
                            compulsion. Lucius Mercello was subjected to the same tortures.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Squillus named many. And Cassius ordered them to be killed,
                            except those who redeemed themselves with a fine.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">For he openly agreed upon six million sesterces with Calpurnius
                            and five million with Quintus Sestius, men who, although extremely
                            guilty, were fined. Nevertheless, the fact that the danger to his life
                            and the pain of his wounds had been discharged for a fine signified that
                            his cruelty had contended with his greed.</seg></p>
                    <p n="56"><seg n="1">A few days later he (sc. Cassius) received a letter sent by
                            Caesar from which he learned that Pompey, defeated in battle and having
                            lost his troops, had fled.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Upon learning this he experienced pleasure mixed with resentment.
                            The news of victory elicited joy [or? In announcing the victory he
                            expressed joy?], but the conclusion of the war put an end to the lax
                            discipline of the times. So uncertain was his mind as to whether it
                            preferred to fear nothing or to be permitted everything.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Once his wounds had healed he summoned everyone who had provided
                            him with funds and ordered the funds to be recorded as having been
                            received (sc. by them as loans from him). Whenever he seemed to have
                            imposed too small a burden on anyone, he requisitioned more money.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">He instituted a levy of men of equestrian rank. His practice was
                            invite these men, drafted from every community and colony and thoroughly
                            cowed by (sc. the prospect of) military service overseas, to purchase an
                            exemption from the military oath. This was a great source of revenue but
                            neverthess began to create greater hatred.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">After finishing this business he purified the entire army. The
                            legions and auxiliary troops that he was going to take to Africa he sent
                            to the crossing point.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">He himself went to Seville to inspect the fleet that he was
                            preparing. He lingered there because he had put forth an edict
                            throughout his province ordering into his presence those from whom he
                            had requisitioned funds and who had not yet made their contributions.
                            This summons disturbed everyone greatly. </seg></p>
                    <p n="57"><seg n="1">Meanwhile, Lucius Titius, who at the time was serving as
                            military tribune in the indigenous legion, reported that it had parted
                            company with the 30th legion (which the legate Quintus Cassius was
                            leading simultaneously) when he was encamped at the town Leptis—a mutiny
                            had occurred and some centurions (who were not permitting the removal of
                            the standards) had been killed—and marched in the direction of the
                            second legion. This was being led to the strait by another route.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Upon learning of this, he (sc. Cassius Longinus) left by night
                            with 5 cohorts of men from the 21st legion, and early in the morning he
                            arrived at †noctu† (or (sc. at Leptis?)). Having delayed there for one
                            day, to get a clear view of what was happening, he marched to
                            Carmo.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When the 30th legion, the 21st legion, 4 cohorts from the 5th
                            legion, and all the cavalry had assembled there, he heard that 4 cohorts
                            (sc. of the 5th legion), overpowered by soldiers of the indigenous
                            legion near Obucula, had reached the second (sc. legion) along with
                            them, and that they had all joined forces there and chosen †in† Torius
                            from Italica as leader.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Having quickly held a council, he (sc. Cassius) sent his quaestor
                            Marcellus to Corduba so as to secure that town in his possession, and he
                            sent his legate Quintus Cassius to Seville.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">After a few days news was brought to him that the Corduban
                            assembly had defected from him, and that Marcellus, motivated either by
                            his own volition or by necessity (for reports about this vary), was
                            acting in accord with the Cordubans, and that 2 cohorts from the 5th
                            legion (which had been in the garrison at Corduba) were doing the
                            same.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">Enraged by these developments, Cassius packed up camp and came to
                            Segovia on the Singiliensen river the next day. Holding an assembly, he
                            tested the morale of the soldiers. He discovered that these were
                            extremely loyal to him not for his own sake but for the absent Caesar's,
                            and that they would refuse no danger provided that the province was
                            restored to Caesar through their agency.</seg></p>
                    <p n="58"><seg n="1">Meanwhile, Torius led the veteran legions to Corduba. And
                            lest it appear that the beginning of dissension had arisen in a mutinous
                            disposition that he or his soldiers possessed, and at the same time to
                            counter Quintus Cassius (who in Caesar's name seemed to have more
                            substantial resources at his disposal) with an equally powerful
                            authority, he kept saying openly that he wanted to recover the province
                            for Pompey.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Perhaps he did this, too, from hatred for Caesar and love of
                            Pompey, whose name carried much power among those legions that had been
                            under the control of M. Varro. His intentions in (sc. doing) it were a
                            matter of widespread conjecture. But this is certainly the pretext he
                            used.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The soldiers' declarations were so explicit that they had the
                            name of Gnaeus Pompey engraved on their shields.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">The citizen community in large numbers—not only of men but also
                            of matrons and youths in citizen dress—came out to meet the legions and
                            pleaded with them not to plunder Corduba with a hostile attack: for they
                            agreed with everyone against Cassius, they said, and begged that they
                            not be compelled to act against Caesar.</seg></p>
                    <p n="59"><seg n="1">The army, moved by the entreaties and tears of such a great
                            multitude, when it saw that the name and memory of Gnaeus Pompey was not
                            necessary for taking punitive action against Cassius, and that Longinus
                            was hated as much by all Caesarians as by all Pompeians, and that they
                            themselves were unable to lead the citizen community or Marcus Marcellus
                            against Caesar’s cause, removed the name of Pompey from their shields,
                            accepted Marcellus, who began declaring himself a defender of Caesar’s
                            cause, as their leader, named him praetor, joined themselves to the
                            citizen community, and established their camp at Corduba.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Cassius made his camp two days later about four miles from
                            Corduba on the other side of the river Baetis in a high place within
                            sight of the town. He sent letters to King Bogud in Mauretania and to
                            Marcus Lepidus, the proconsul in nearer Spain, that he should come with
                            assistance for him and the province as soon as possible, for the cause
                            of Caesar. He himself, in a hostile manner, devastated the fields of
                            Corduba and burned the buildings.</seg></p>
                    <p n="60"><seg n="1">Because of the heinous and base character of this action,
                            the legions that had taken Marcellus as their leader ran to him: they
                            should be led out into battle, and there should be a chance for them to
                            fight before, so humiliatingly, the finest and most beloved possessions
                            of the Cordubans were consumed in their own sight by plunder, sword, and
                            fire.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Marcellus, although he thought that combat was utterly wretched,
                            because the loss for both the victor and the defeated would similarly
                            redound on Caesar, and it was not within his official capacity, led his
                            legions across the Baetis and drew up his battle line.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When he noticed that Cassius had drawn up his line opposite, in
                            front of his own camp and on higher ground, having given the explanation
                            that he <surplus>Cassius</surplus> was not descending onto level ground,
                            Marcellus persuaded his soldiers to withdraw into the camp. Thus he
                            began to bring back his troops.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Cassius, having attacked the retreating legions with cavalry, in
                            which resource he was strong and knew Marcellus was weak, killed many of
                            those in the rear on the river banks.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Since it had become known from this loss what problem and
                            difficulty the river crossing posed, Marcellus moved his camp across the
                            Baetis. And both men frequently led out their legions into the battle
                            line, but they did not fight because of the difficulties of the
                            location.</seg></p>
                    <p n="61"><seg n="1">Marcellus was much stronger in infantry forces. For he had
                            veteran legions, experienced in many battles. Cassius was more confident
                            of the loyalty than of the valor of his legions.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Thus, when camp had been moved near camp and Marcellus had
                            occupied a suitable place for a stronghold from which to be able to keep
                            Cassius' forces from water, Longinus, afraid lest he be enclosed by some
                            kind of siege in regions that were unfamiliar and unfriendly to him, set
                            out from camp in silence at night and made for Ulia with a swift
                            journey, because he believed the town was faithful to him.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">There he placed his camp so closely conjoined to the walls that
                            he was protected on all sides from an attack by both the nature of the
                            site (for Ulia is placed on a high mountain) and the city's very
                            fortification.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">Marcellus followed him, and moved his camp near to Cassius’ camp,
                            as close to Ulia as possible. And when the nature of the place was known
                            to him, he was led by necessity to the point to which he very much
                            wanted to bring matters, namely, not to fight (for if there was a
                            possibility of conflict, he was not going to be able to resist his eager
                            troops) and not to allow Cassius to wander too far, lest more peoples
                            suffer those things that the Cordubans had suffered.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">With his strongholds placed in suitable locations and his
                            earthworks making a continuous circuit of the town, he closed in Ulia
                            and Cassius with fortifications.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">But before these could be finished Longinus sent out his entire
                            cavalry. He believed that this would be useful to him if it did not
                            allow Marcellus to forage and collect provisions, but that it would be a
                            great disadvantage if, shut in by the siege and useless, it consumed
                            necessary provisions. </seg></p>
                    <p n="62"><seg n="1">In a few days King Bogus, having received Quintus Cassius'
                            letter, came with his forces, and he joined to the legion which he had
                            brought with him several auxiliary cohorts of Spanish men.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For as is customary to happen in civil conflicts, at that time in
                            Spain several communities were supporting the affairs of Cassius, more
                            were favorable toward Marcellus.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">Bogus approached with his forces to Marcellus’ outer
                            fortifications. There was fierce fighting on both sides, and this
                            happened frequently, with Fortune frequently shifting victory to each
                            side; nevertheless, Marcellus was never driven away from his
                            earthworks.</seg></p>
                    <p n="63"><seg n="1">Meanwhile, Lepidus came to Ulia from the nearer province
                            with thirty-five legionary cohorts and a great number of cavalry and his
                            remaining auxiliary troops, with the intention of resolving without any
                            prejudice the conflicts of Cassius and Marcellus. </seg>
                        <seg n="2">Marcellus entrusted and offered himself without any hesitation to
                            this man when he came. Cassius, however, remained within his defenses,
                            either because he thought that he was due more authority than Marcellus
                            or because he was concerned lest Lepidus’ mind had been won over
                            beforehand by his adversary's compliance. </seg>
                        <seg n="3">Lepidus made camp at Ulia and shared everything with Marcellus.
                            He ordered that there be no fighting. He invited Cassius to come out and
                            gave his word for everything.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">When Cassius had hesitated for a long time as to what he should
                            do and how much trust he should place in Lepidus, and discovered no
                            outcome for his plan if he persisted in his opinion, he demanded that
                            the fortifications be broken up and that a free exit be given to
                            him.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">With not only a truce arranged but when they (sc. Lepidus and
                            Marcellus) were leveling their now nearly constructed earthworks and the
                            fortifications’ guards had been removed, the king's auxiliary troops
                            made an attack against the stronghold of Marcellus that was closest to
                            the king's camp—when no one was expecting it, if in fact that ‘no one’
                            included Cassius, for there was doubt concerning his complicity—and
                            overpowered many soldiers there. </seg>
                        <seg n="6">And had the battle not been quickly broken up by the righteous
                            anger and help of Lepidus, a greater disaster would have been
                            sustained.</seg></p>
                    <p n="64"><seg n="1">When a way had been made open for Cassius, Marcellus joined
                            his camp to Lepidus. Lepidus and Marcellus (sc. set out) simultaneously
                            for Corduba, Cassius set out with his forces for Carmo.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Around the same time Trebonius the proconsul came to take control
                            of the province. When Cassius learned about his arrival he placed the
                            legions that he had had with him, as well as the cavalry, into their
                            winter quarters. After quickly gathering all of his possessions he
                            hastened to Malaca and embarked there even though the season was
                            unfavorable for sailing, so that he might not have to entrust himself to
                            Lepidus, Trebonius, and Marcellus, as he himself declared, so that he
                            might not make a journey with lesser dignity through that province of
                            which a great part had abandoned him, as his friends kept saying, and so
                            that the cash collected from boundless pillaging might not come into
                            anyone’s power, as others thought.</seg>
                        <seg n="3"> When he, having made progress in weather that was favorable for
                            winter, had put into the Ebro river to avoid the night, setting out
                            thence, despite the storm growing a little more violent, believing that
                            he would sail no more dangerously than before, with the incoming waves
                            blocking the river mouth he perished right in the narrow outlet after
                            his ship sank since he could neither maneuver his ship because of the
                            river’s force nor keep it straight in such great waves.</seg></p>
                    <p n="65"><seg n="1">When Caesar had come to Syria from Egypt and learned from
                            those who had come to him from Rome (and found out from letters from the
                            city) that many things at Rome were being administrated badly and
                            inefficiently, and that no part of the Republic was being run well
                            enough, because, so they said, both pernicious seditions were arising
                            from in-fighting among (sc. plebeian) tribunes and, owing to
                            favor-seeking and carelessness on the part of the military tribunes and
                            (sc. of those) who were in charge of the legions, many things were being
                            done contrary to military custom and practice, things that tended to
                            relax discipline and severity, and when Caesar saw that all these things
                            demanded his presence, he still thought it preferable to leave those
                            provinces and regions into which he had come composed in such a way that
                            they would be free from internal dissension, accept rights and laws, and
                            dispense with their fear of foreign enemies.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He hoped to fix these things quickly in Syria, Cilicia, and Asia
                            because these provinces were not being threatened with war. In Bithynia
                            and Pontus he saw that a greater burden hung over him.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">For he heard that Pharnaces had not left Pontus, and he didn’t
                            think he would, since he had become very arrogant from the favorable
                            battle that he had fought against Domitius Calvinus.</seg>
                        <seg n="4"> Spending time in almost every city of significant importance
                            (sc. in Syria), Caesar allocated rewards, both man by man and publicly,
                            to those who deserved well of him, held hearings about and settled
                            long-standing legal questions, (sc. and) after receiving into his trust
                            kings, tyrants, and rulers neighboring the province—who had all flocked
                            to him—on the condition that they guard and defend the province, sent
                            them away as very good friends to both himself and the Roman people.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="66"><seg n="1">After spending a few days in that province, he left his
                            friend and kinsman Sextus Caesar in charge of the legions and Syria. He
                            himself set out to Cilicia in the same fleet in which he had come.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He called all the cities of this province to Tarsus, which was
                            practically the noblest and strongest town in all Cilicia.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">When all the affairs of the province and the neighboring cities
                            were settled there, owing to his desire to set out to make war he
                            delayed no longer, and stopping at Mazaca for two days after forced
                            marches through Cappadocia, Comana <gap reason="lost"/> the shrine of
                            Bellona, the oldest and holiest in Cappadocia, which is worshipped with
                            such great fervor that the priest of this goddess is considered second
                            to the king by the consent of that people in majesty, command, and
                            power.</seg>
                        <seg n="4"> He awarded it to the very noble Lycomedes, a Bithynian who was
                            born in the royal family of the Cappadocians and was seeking that
                            priesthood again, his right (sc. to it) being not at all in doubt but
                            nevertheless long discontinued on account of the adverse circumstances
                            of his ancestors and a change in the royal line.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Caesar handed over to Ariarathes, the brother of Ariobarzanes,
                            because both of them deserved well of the Republic, so that the
                            inheritance of the kingdom might not tempt Ariarathes, and so that an
                            heir to the kingdom might not threaten <gap reason="lost"/> to
                            Ariobarzanes to be under his power and command. Caesar began to complete
                            with similar haste the journey he had begun.</seg></p>
                    <p n="67">
                        <seg n="1">When he (sc. Caesar) had arrived near Pontus and the territory of
                            Gallograecia, Deiotarus, tetrarch of almost all of Gallograecia at that
                            time—a title that the other tetrarchs kept asserting was granted neither
                            by laws nor by custom, yet a man without doubt named king of Lesser
                            Armenia by the senate—with his royal emblems put aside, and not only in
                            ordinary clothing but even in the garb of the accused, came as a
                            suppliant to Caesar in order to beseech (sc. Caesar) to forgive him the
                            fact that, as he was located in a part of the world that had no
                            Caesarian garrisons and was under the compulsion of armies and orders,
                            he had been in the camp of Gnaeus Pompey.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">For (sc. he said that) his obligation was not to be a judge of
                            the disputes of the Roman people but to obey orders on the spot.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="68"><seg n="1">In reply to him, Caesar, after he had recalled his own very
                            numerous services, which he as consul bestowed upon him by public
                            decrees, and after he had argued that his (sc. Deiotarus') defense could
                            not contain any excuse of ignorance on his part, since a man of such
                            great foresight and attentiveness was able to know who held the city and
                            Italy, where the senate and Roman people were, where the state was, plus
                            who was consul after Lucius Lentulus and Gaius Marcellus, nevertheless
                            he said that he was pardoned this deed because of his own earlier
                            services, his long-standing hospitality and friendship, the man's status
                            and age, and the requests of those numerous hosts and friends who had
                            assembled to beg for mercy towards Deiotarus; (sc. he said) that he
                            would examine the disputes of the tetrarchs later. He restored the royal
                            clothing to him.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">As for the legion drawn from the stock of his fellow citizens
                            that Deiotarus had built up with our nature and training, he ordered
                            (sc. him) to bring it and his entire cavalry along to wage
                        war.</seg></p>
                    <p n="69">
                        <seg n="1">When he had come to Pontus and had collected into on place all of
                            his forces, which were middling in number and experience in war—for,
                            with the sixth legion excepted, which he had brought with him from
                            Alexandria, a veteran (sc. legion) formerly engaged in many hardships
                            and dangers and smaller by a large number of soldiers, partly from the
                            difficulty of the marches and voyages and partly owing to the frequency
                            of combat, to such a degree that there were fewer than a thousand men in
                            it—there were three legions remaining, one belonging to Deiotarus, two
                            that had been in the battle that we wrote Gnaeus Domitius had with
                            Pharnaces.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Envoys sent by Pharnaces approached Caesar and pleaded especially
                            that his arrival not be hostile: for Pharnaces, (sc. they said), would
                            do everything that had been ordered.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">And they pointed out most of all that Pharnaces had been willing
                            to give no auxiliary forces to Pompey against Caesar, whereas Deiotarus,
                            who had given (sc. auxiliary forces to Pompey), had nevertheless made
                            amends to him (i.e., Caesar).</seg></p>
                    <p n="70"><seg n="1">Caesar answered that he would be very fair to Pharnaces, if
                            he (sc. Pharnaces) was going to do what he was promising.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">He did, however, warn the envoys in mild terms, as he was
                            accustomed, that they should not criticize Deiotarus to him or boast
                            excessively about this service, namely, that they had not sent auxiliary
                            troops to Pompey.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">For (sc. he said) both that he did nothing more gladly than
                            forgive suppliants and that he was unable to pardon the public abuse of
                            provinces for those who had been dutiful towards himself.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">And yet as for the very service they were pointing out, (sc. he
                            said) that it had been more advantageous for Pharnaces, who had made
                            provisions so as not to be defeated, than for himself, to whom the
                            immortal gods had granted victory.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">And so (sc. he said) that he pardoned Pharnaces for the great and
                            serious abuse of the Roman citizens who had been trading in Pontus,
                            since he was not able to make them whole again.</seg>
                        <seg n="6">For (sc. he said) that he was not able to restore their lost life
                            to the slaughtered nor their manhood to the castrated; and Roman
                            citizens had indeed endured this punishment, more heavy-handed than
                            death.</seg>
                        <seg n="7">But (sc. he said that) he (sc. Pharnaces) should leave Pontus
                            immediately and return the staff of the publicani and restore to Roman
                            allies and citizens the remaining things that were under his
                            control.</seg>
                        <seg n="8">(Sc. Caesar said that) if he (sc. Pharnaces) had acted, he should
                            at that point send to him (sc. Caesar) the tributes and gifts that
                            commanders were accustomed to receive from friends after successes. For
                            Pharnaces had sent him a golden crown. After returning these answers, he
                            sent the envoys back.</seg></p>
                    <p n="71"><seg n="1">But Pharnaces, having promised everything generously since
                            he was hoping that Caesar, hastening and en route, would even trust his
                            promises more freely than the situation allowed, so that he (sc. Caesar)
                            might set out sooner and more honorably for more important matters—for
                            everybody knew that Caesar was being called back to the city for many
                            reasons—began acting more slowly, demanding a later day for departure,
                            interposing contractual agreements, in short, obstructing.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Caesar, since he recognized the man’s craftiness, was compelled
                            to do by necessity what, at other times, he had been accustomed to do by
                            nature, namely, to do battle more quickly than anyone
                        expected.</seg></p>
                    <p n="72"><seg n="1">Zela is a town that lies in Pontus, (sc. the town) itself
                            suitably fortified given that it stands on open ground. For a hill,
                            natural but like one made by hand, supports a wall at a rather elevated
                            height on all sides.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Many large hills separated by valleys surround this town. And the
                            highest of these, a single hill that on account of Mithridates’ victory
                            and Triarius’ misfortune and the defeat of our army ([sc. it is]
                            practically connected to the town by relatively high ground and paths)
                            has a great notoriety in those parts and is not much more than three
                            miles away from Zela—</seg><seg n="3"> this location Pharnaces occupied
                            with all of his troops after the old earthworks of the camp that was
                            lucky for his father were repaired.</seg></p>
                    <p n="73"><seg n="1">Caesar, when he had placed camp five miles away from the
                            enemy and saw that the valleys by which the royal camp was fortified
                            would fortify his own camp by the same interval, at any rate if the
                            enemy had not seized these locations previously—they were much closer to
                            the royal camp—, ordered that material for a rampart be brought inside
                            the defenses.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">After this was done quickly, with all the legions readied for
                            action the next night at the fourth watch and the baggage left behind in
                            camp, at dawn, with the enemy unaware, he (sc. Caesar) seized that very
                            spot where Mithridates had fought a successful battle against
                            Triarius.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">To this spot he then ordered the slaves to convey from the camp
                            all the collected material, so that no soldier would leave the defensive
                            work, since it was by a space of no more than a mile that an interceding
                            valley divided the enemy’s camp from the preliminary defensive work of
                            Caesar’s camp.</seg></p>
                    <p n="74"><seg n="1">Pharnaces, when he suddenly noticed this at dawn, drew up
                            all of his troops in front of his camp. Given the locations' large
                            intervening height differential (i.e., between the camps of Caesar and
                            Pharnaces), Caesar thought that these troops were drawn up in accordance
                            with a common military custom, either in order to slow down his
                            fortification work, so that more men might be held at arms, or for the
                            sake of showing royal confidence, lest Pharnaces seem to defend his
                            location more by fortification than by hand.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">Thus Caesar was not deterred from having the remaining part of
                            his army constructed the defensive work while the front line was drawn
                            up in front of the trench.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">But Pharnaces—whether compelled by the good fortune of his
                            location, or induced by omens and religious scruples, which we later
                            heard that he had obeyed, or after discovering how few of our troops
                            were at arms, since he had believed that the great multitude of slaves
                            that was carrying the material for a rampart in the manner of everyday
                            fortification work was a great multitude of soldiers, or even out of
                            confidence in his veteran army, which his officers boasted had fought in
                            22 pitched battles and won each time, along with contempt for our army,
                            which he knew had been beaten by himself when Domitius was
                            commander—after the decision to fight was entered into, began to descend
                            via the precipitous valley.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">For some time Caesar kept laughing at the empty show and the
                            massing of soldiers in a spot into which no sane enemy would advance,
                            when in the meantime Pharnaces, with the same pace with which he had
                            descended into the downward-sloping valley, began to climb the steep
                            hill opposing him with his troops in battle formation. </seg></p>
                    <p n="75"><seg n="1">Caesar, shaken by Pharnaces’ unbelievable recklessness or
                            confidence, caught unaware and unprepared, recalled his soldiers from
                            the earthworks, ordered them to take up arms, brought forward his
                            legions, and drew up his line. The sudden agitation produced by this
                            state of affairs brought significant fear to our men.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">When the lines were not yet drawn up the king’s chariots, armed
                            with scythes, dismayed the disorganized soldiers. But the chariots were
                            quickly overwhelmed by a large number of missiles.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">The enemy line followed the chariots. And after raising a shout
                            the forces clashed, with the nature of the place providing much help to
                            Caesar’s forces, but the most help was provided by the benevolence of
                            the immortal gods, who are present in all happenings of war,
                            particularly those in which nothing was able to be effected by
                            reason.</seg></p>
                    <p n="76"><seg n="1">After a great and bitter battle fought at close quarters,
                            the beginning of victory appeared on the right flank, where the veteran
                            sixth legion had been placed. As the enemy forces were being forced away
                            downhill on that side, on the left flank and in the middle of the line,
                            much more slowly but nevertheless with the same gods assisting, all the
                            king’s troops were overwhelmed.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">And having been driven from their position as quickly as they had
                            come up the slope easily, they were under pressure from the disadvantage
                            of the terrain. And so after many of the soldiers had been killed, many
                            others overwhelmed by their comrades falling, those who managed to flee
                            using their speed—but still, having thrown away their weapons—being
                            unarmed, were unable to accomplish anything from higher ground once they
                            had crossed the valley. But our men, carried away by their victory, did
                            not hesitate to move onto unfavorable ground and assault the
                            fortifications.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">With the troops that Pharnaces left as a guard attempting to
                            defend the camp, our men quickly gained possession of the enemy camp. As
                            the entire multitude of his men had been killed or captured, Pharnaces
                            fled with a few of his cavalry.</seg>
                        <seg n="4">If our assault on his camp had not granted him the opportunity to
                            flee more freely, he would have been brought alive into Caesar’s power.
                        </seg></p>
                    <p n="77"><seg n="1">Caesar, so many times a conqueror, was in a state of
                            incredible happiness at such a victory, since he had brought about the
                            end of a very great war with such speed, and he was happier still upon
                            reflecting on the sudden danger, because an easy victory had been arisen
                            out of difficult circumstances.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">On the day after he had retaken Pontus and distributed all of the
                            royal spoils among the soldiers Caesar set out with unencumbered
                            cavalry. He ordered the sixth legion to leave for Italy to receive
                            prizes and honors, sent Deiotarus’ auxiliary forces back home, (sc. and)
                            left two legions in Pontus with Caelius Vinicianus.</seg></p>
                    <p n="78"><seg n="1">Thus he made his way through Gallograecia and Bithynia into
                            Asia and investigated the disputes in all of these provinces and made
                            judgements upon them; he allocated jurisdictions to the tetrarchs,
                            kings, and states.</seg>
                        <seg n="2">As for Mithridates of Pergamum, by whom the situation in Egypt,
                            which I have written about above, was brought to completion auspiciously
                            and quickly, since he was born from a royal bloodline and even educated
                            royally (for Mithridates, king of all Asia, had carried the child off
                            from Pergamum into the camps with him, and kept him there for many
                            years), Caesar made him king of Bosphorus, which had been under
                            Pharnaces’ control, and, by placing a most friendly king between them,
                            defended the Roman provinces from barbarian and hostile kings.</seg>
                        <seg n="3">He also granted Mithridates the tetrarchy over the people of
                            Gallograecia (which had been occupied and held in Deiotarus' possession
                            a few years earlier) by the right of his people and bloodline.</seg>
                        <seg n="5">Nevertheless, he did not delay anywhere longer than the exigency
                            of the sedition in the cities seemed to permit. When these matters were
                            handled most happily and efficiently, he came to Italy more quickly than
                            everyone's expectation.</seg></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <!--
The content of the back matter will be determined in consultation between
        the editor and the staff of the DLL. Because LDLT editions are encoded, the
        matter traditionally found in the back of a printed critical edition may be
        generated by applications instead of having to be entered manually.
        Nevertheless, there is space here for notes, indices, and other kinds of
        information.
-->
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
